<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<country name="Afghanistan" short="AFG">
    <introduction>
        <paragraph>
            Ahmad Shah DURRANI unified the Pashtun tribes and founded Afghanistan in 1747. The country served as a buffer between the British and Russian Empires until it won independence from notional British control in 1919. A brief experiment in increased democracy ended in a 1973 coup and a 1978 communist countercoup. The Soviet Union invaded in 1979 to support the tottering Afghan communist regime, touching off a long and destructive war. The USSR withdrew in 1989 under relentless pressure by internationally supported anti-communist mujahidin rebels. A series of subsequent civil wars saw Kabul finally fall in 1996 to the Taliban, a hardline Pakistani-sponsored movement that emerged in 1994 to end the country's civil war and anarchy. Following the 11 September 2001 terrorist attacks, a US, Allied, and anti-Taliban Northern Alliance military action toppled the Taliban for sheltering Usama BIN LADIN.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            A UN-sponsored Bonn Conference in 2001 established a process for political reconstruction that included the adoption of a new constitution, a presidential election in 2004, and National Assembly elections in 2005. In December 2004, Hamid KARZAI became the first democratically elected president of Afghanistan, and the National Assembly was inaugurated the following December. KARZAI was reelected in August 2009 for a second term. The 2014 presidential election was the country's first to include a runoff, which featured the top two vote-getters from the first round, Abdullah ABDULLAH and Ashraf GHANI. Throughout the summer of 2014, their campaigns disputed the results and traded accusations of fraud, leading to a US-led diplomatic intervention that included a full vote audit as well as political negotiations between the two camps. In September 2014, GHANI and ABDULLAH agreed to form the Government of National Unity, with GHANI inaugurated as president and ABDULLAH elevated to the newly-created position of chief executive officer. The day after the inauguration, the GHANI administration signed the US-Afghan Bilateral Security Agreement and NATO Status of Forces Agreement, which provide the legal basis for the post-2014 international military presence in Afghanistan. After two postponements, the next presidential election was held in September 2019.
        </paragraph>
        <paragraph>
            The Taliban remains a serious challenge for the Afghan Government in almost every province. The Taliban still considers itself the rightful government of Afghanistan, and it remains a capable and confident insurgent force fighting for the withdrawal of foreign military forces from Afghanistan, establishment of sharia law, and rewriting of the Afghan constitution. In 2019, negotiations between the US and the Taliban in Doha entered their highest level yet, building on momentum that began in late 2018. Underlying the negotiations is the unsettled state of Afghan politics, and prospects for a sustainable political settlement remain unclear.
        </paragraph>
    </introduction>
    <geography>
        <span name="Location" align="top">Southern Asia, north and west of Pakistan, east of Iran</span>
        <span name="Continent" align="top">Asia</span>
        <span name="Coastline" align="top" newline="1">none</span>
        <coordinates latitude="33.00" lattype="N" longitude="65.00" longtype="E" />
        <area total="652230" land="652230" water="0" rank="42">almost six times the size of Virginia; slightly smaller than Texas</area>
        <boundaries total="5987" count="6">
            <boundary with="China" length="91" />
            <boundary with="Iran" length="921" />
            <boundary with="Pakistan" length="2670" />
            <boundary with="Tajikistan" length="1357" />
            <boundary with="Turkmenistan" length="804" />
            <boundary with="Uzbekistan" length="144" />
        </boundaries>
        <maritime_claims />
        <elevation mean="1884" lowestalt="258" lowest="Amu Darya" highest="Noshak" highestalt="7492" />
        <land agricultural="58.1" arable="11.8" arablecrops="0.3" arablepasture="46" forest="2.07" other="39" irrigated="32.080" />
        <span name="Climate">cold winters and hot summers</span>
        <span name="Terrain" newline="1">mostly rugged mountains; plains in north and southwest</span>
        <span name="Distribution" newline="1">populations tend to cluster in the foothills and periphery of the rugged Hindu Kush range; smaller groups are found in many of the country's interior valleys; in general, the east is more densely settled, while the south is sparsely populated</span>
        <span name="Environment - issues" newline="1">limited natural freshwater resources; inadequate supplies of potable water; soil degradation; overgrazing; deforestation (much of the remaining forests are being cut down for fuel and building materials); desertification; air and water pollution in overcrowded urban areas</span>
        <span name="Environment - agreements">party to: Biodiversity, Climate Change, Desertification, Endangered Species, Environmental Modification, Marine Dumping, Ozone Layer Protection</span>
        <span name="Resources" align="right" newline="1">natural gas, petroleum, coal, copper, chromite, talc, barites, sulfur, lead, zinc, iron ore, salt, precious and semiprecious stones, arable land</span>
        <span name="Hazards" align="right" newline="1">damaging earthquakes occur in Hindu Kush mountains; flooding; droughts</span>
        <span name="Note" align="right">landlocked; the Hindu Kush mountains that run northeast to southwest divide the northern provinces from the rest of the country; the highest peaks are in the northern Vakhan (Wakhan Corridor)</span>
    </geography>
    <people_and_society>
        <population count="36643815" ranking="39" />
        <nationality noun="Afghan(s)" adjective="Afghan" />
        <ethnic_groups>Pashtun, Tajik, Hazara, Uzbek, other (includes smaller numbers of Baloch, Turkmen, Nuristani, Pamiri, Arab, Gujar, Brahui, Qizilbash, Aimaq, Pashai, and Kyrghyz) (2015)</ethnic_groups>
        <languages>
            <language name="Afghan Persian or Dari" percent="77" official="true" />
            <language name="Pashto" percent="48" official="true" />
            <language name="Uzbek" percent="11" />
            <language name="English" percent="6" />
            <language name="Turkmen" percent="3" />
            <language name="Urdu" percent="3" />
        </languages>
        <religions>
            <religion name="Sunni (Muslim)" percent="87" />
            <religion name="Shia (Muslim)" percent="12" />
            <religion name="other" percent="1" />
        </religions>
        <age_structure>
            <age min="0" max="14" percent="40.62" male="7562703" female="7321646" />
            <age min="15" max="24" percent="21.26" male="3960044" female="3828670" />
            <age min="25" max="54" percent="31.44" male="5858675" female="5661887" />
            <age min="55" max="64" percent="4.01" male="724597" female="744910" />
            <age min="65" max="120" percent="2.68" male="451852" female="528831" />
        </age_structure>
        <dependency_ratio total="88.8" youth="75.3" elderly="4.8" potential="21" />
        <rate_per_thousand birth="36.7" death="12.7" />
        <sex_ratio total="1.03" >
            <age min="0" max="14" male_over_female="1.03" />
            <age min="15" max="24" male_over_female="1.03" />
            <age min="25" max="54" male_over_female="1.03" />
            <age min="55" max="64" male_over_female="0.97" />
            <age min="65" max="120" male_over_female="0.85" />
        </sex_ratio>
        <average_mother first_birth_age="19.9" mortality_rate="638" children="4.82" />
        <drinking_water total="70.2" urban="95.9" rural="61.4" />
        <sanitation_facility_access total="53.2" rural="43" urban="83.6" />
        <diseases>
            <disease type="food or waterborne">bacterial diarrhea, hepatitis A, and typhoid fever</disease>
            <disease type="vectorborne">Crimea-Congo hemorrhagic fever, malaria</disease>
        </diseases>
        <health_expenditure>11.8</health_expenditure>
        <statistics>
            <statistic name="median_age" total="19.5" male="19.4" female="19.5" ranking="202">Median age</statistic>
            <statistic name="infant_mortality" total="104.3" male="111.3" female="96.9" ranking="1">Infant mortality</statistic>
            <statistic name="life_expectancy" total="52.8" male="51.4" female="54.4" ranking="228">Life expectancy</statistic>
            <statistic name="literacy" total="43" male="55.5" female="29.8">Literacy</statistic>
            <statistic name="school_life_expectancy" total="10" male="13" female="8">School life expectancy</statistic>
            <statistic name="youth_unemployment" total="17.6" male="16.3" female="21.4" ranking="75">Youth unemployment</statistic>
        </statistics>
    </people_and_society>
    <government>
        <span name="Country name" align="top">Islamic Republic of Afghanistan (short Afghanistan)</span>
        <span name="Type of government" align="top">presidential Islamic republic</span>
        <span name="Capital" align="top">Kabul</span>
        <span name="UTC time" align="top" newline="1">UTC+4.5</span>
        <span name="Independence day" align="top">19th August 1919</span>
        <span name="Legal system" align="top">mixed legal system of civil, customary, and Islamic (sharia) law</span>
        <span name="Suffrage" align="top" newline="1">at the age of 18</span>

        <divisions count="34" name="province">Badakhshan, Badghis, Baghlan, Balkh, Bamyan, Daykundi, Farah, Faryab, Ghazni, Ghor, Helmand, Herat, Jowzjan, Kabul, Kandahar, Kapisa, Khost, Kunar, Kunduz, Laghman, Logar, Nangarhar, Nimroz, Nuristan, Paktika, Paktiya, Panjshir, Parwan, Samangan, Sar-e Pul, Takhar, Uruzgan, Wardak, Zabul</divisions>

        <citizenships>
            <citizenship by="birth">no</citizenship>
            <citizenship by="descent only">at least one parent must have been born in - and continuously lived in - Afghanistan</citizenship>
        </citizenships>

        <executive>
            <span name="Chief of state">
                President of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan Ashraf GHANI (since 29 September 2014); CEO Abdullah ABDULLAH, Dr. (since 29 September 2014); First Vice President Abdul Rashid DOSTAM (since 29 September 2014); Second Vice President Sarwar DANESH (since 29 September 2014); First Deputy CEO Khyal Mohammad KHAN; Second Deputy CEO Mohammad MOHAQQEQ; note - the president is both chief of state and head of government
            </span>
            <span name="Head of government">
                President of the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan Ashraf GHANI (since 29 September 2014); CEO Abdullah ABDULLAH, Dr. (since 29 September 2014); First Vice President Abdul Rashid DOSTAM (since 29 September 2014); Second Vice President Sarwar DANESH (since 29 September 2014); First Deputy CEO Khyal Mohammad KHAN; Second Deputy CEO Mohammad MOHAQQEQ
            </span>
            <span name="Cabinet">Cabinet consists of 25 ministers appointed by the president, approved by the National Assembly</span>
            <span name="Elections">president directly elected by absolute majority popular vote in 2 rounds if needed for a 5-year term (eligible for a second term); election last held on 28 September 2019 (next to be held in 2024)</span>
            <span name="Election results">Ashraf GHANI declared winner by the Independent Election Commission on 18 February 2020; Ashraf GHANI 50.6%, Abdullah ABDULLAH, Dr. 39.5%, other 0.9%</span>
        </executive>

        <legislative>
            <span name="Description">
                bicameral National Assembly consists of:
                Meshrano Jirga or House of Elders (102 seats; 34 members indirectly elected by absolute majority vote in 2 rounds if needed by district councils to serve 3-year terms, 34 indirectly elected by absolute majority vote in 2 rounds if needed by provincial councils to serve 4-year terms, and 34 appointed by the president from nominations by civic groups, political parties, and the public, of which 17 must be women, 2 must represent the disabled, and 2 must be Kuchi nomads; presidential appointees serve 5-year terms)
                Wolesi Jirga or House of People (250 seats; members directly elected in multi-seat constituencies by proportional representation vote to serve 5-year terms)
            </span>
            <span name="Elections">
                Meshrano Jirga - district councils - within 5 days of installation; provincial councils - within 15 days of installation; presidential appointees - within 2 weeks after the presidential inauguration
                Wolesi Jirga - last held on 20 October 2018) (next to be held in 2023)
            </span>
            <span name="Election results">
                Meshrano Jirga - percent of vote by party - NA; seats by party - NA; composition - men 84, women 18, percent of women 17.6%
                Wolesi Jirga - percent of vote by party NA; seats by party - NA; composition - NA
            </span>
        </legislative>

        <judicial>
            <span name="Highest courts">Supreme Court or Stera Mahkama (consists of the supreme court chief and 8 justices organized into criminal, public security, civil, and commercial divisions or dewans)</span>
            <span name="Judge selection">court chief and justices appointed by the president with the approval of the Wolesi Jirga; court chief and justices serve single 10-year terms</span>
            <span name="Subordinate courts">Appeals Courts; Primary Courts; Special Courts for issues including narcotics, security, property, family, and juveniles</span>
        </judicial>

        <flag>
            <image>afg_flag.jpg</image>
            <description>
                three equal vertical bands of black (hoist side), red, and green, with the national emblem in white centered on the red band and slightly overlapping the other 2 bands; the center of the emblem features a mosque with pulpit and flags on either side, below the mosque are Eastern Arabic numerals for the solar year 1298 (1919 in the Gregorian calendar, the year of Afghan independence from the UK); this central image is circled by a border consisting of sheaves of wheat on the left and right, in the upper-center is an Arabic inscription of the Shahada (Muslim creed) below which are rays of the rising sun over the Takbir (Arabic expression meaning "God is great"), and at bottom center is a scroll bearing the name Afghanistan; black signifies the past, red is for the blood shed for independence, and green can represent either hope for the future, agricultural prosperity, or Islam
            </description>
        </flag>

        <span name="Political parties" align="right">72 parties</span>
        <span name="International organizations" align="right" newline="1">
            ADB, CICA, CP, ECO, EITI (candidate country), FAO, G-77, IAEA, IBRD, ICAO, ICC (NGOs), ICCt, ICRM, IDA, IDB, IFAD, IFC, IFRCS, ILO, IMF, Interpol, IOC, IOM, IPU, ISO (correspondent), ITSO, ITU, ITUC (NGOs), MIGA, NAM, OIC, OPCW, OSCE (partner), SAARC, SACEP, SCO (dialogue member), UN, UNAMA, UNCTAD, UNESCO, UNHCR, UNIDO, UNWTO, UPU, WCO, WFTU (NGOs), WHO, WIPO, WMO, WTO
        </span>
        <span name="Constitution - history" align="right" newline="1">several previous; latest drafted 14 December 2003 - 4 January 2004, signed 16 January 2004, ratified 26 January 2004</span>
        <span name="Constitution - amendments" align="right" newline="1">proposed by a commission formed by presidential decree followed by the convention of a Grand Council (Loya Jirga) decreed by the president; passage requires at least two-thirds majority vote of the Loya Jirga membership and endorsement by the president</span>
        <span name="Symbols" align="right">lion; national colors: red, green, black</span>
        <span name="Anthem" align="right">"Milli Surood" (National Anthem)</span>
    </government>
    <economy>
        <span name="Overview" align="top">
            Despite improvements in life expectancy, incomes, and literacy since 2001, Afghanistan is extremely poor, landlocked, and highly dependent on foreign aid. Much of the population continues to suffer from shortages of housing, clean water, electricity, medical care, and jobs. Corruption, insecurity, weak governance, lack of infrastructure, and the Afghan Government's difficulty in extending rule of law to all parts of the country pose challenges to future economic growth. Afghanistan's living standards are among the lowest in the world. Since 2014, the economy has slowed, in large part because of the withdrawal of nearly 100,000 foreign troops that had artificially inflated the country’s economic growth.
            The international community remains committed to Afghanistan's development, pledging over $83 billion at ten donors' conferences between 2003 and 2016. In October 2016, the donors at the Brussels conference pledged an additional $3.8 billion in development aid annually from 2017 to 2020. Even with this help, Government of Afghanistan still faces number of challenges, including low revenue collection, anemic job creation, high levels of corruption, weak government capacity, and poor public infrastructure.
            In 2017 Afghanistan's growth rate was only marginally above that of the 2014-2016 average. The drawdown of international security forces that started in 2012 has negatively affected economic growth, as a substantial portion of commerce, especially in the services sector, has catered to the ongoing international troop presence in the country. Afghan President Ashraf GHANI Ahmadzai is dedicated to instituting economic reforms to include improving revenue collection and fighting corruption. The government has implemented reforms to the budget process and in some other areas. However, many other reforms will take time to implement and Afghanistan will remain dependent on international donor support over the next several years.
        </span>

        <gdp_values>
            <gdp_value type="value">69.45</gdp_value>
            <gdp_value type="exchange rate">20.24</gdp_value>
            <gdp_value type="per capita">2000</gdp_value>
            <gdp_value type="exports" ranking="170">0.784</gdp_value>
            <gdp_value type="imports" ranking="113">7.616</gdp_value>
        </gdp_values>

        <rates>
            <rate type="unemployment_rate">23.9</rate>
            <rate type="below_poverty_line">54.5</rate>
            <rate type="public_debt">7</rate>
            <rate type="inflation_rate">5</rate>
            <rate type="growth_rate">2.7</rate>
            <rate type="gross_national_saving">22.7</rate>
        </rates>

        <compositions>
            <factor name="end use">
                <composition for="household">81.6</composition>
                <composition for="government">12</composition>
                <composition for="investment_fixed_capital">17.2</composition>
                <composition for="investment_inventories">30</composition>
                <composition for="export">6.7</composition>
                <composition for="import">-47.6</composition>
            </factor>
            <factor name="sector of origin">
                <composition for="agriculture">23</composition>
                <composition for="industry">21.1</composition>
                <composition for="services">55.9</composition>
            </factor>
        </compositions>

        <occupations>
            <occupation name="agriculture">44.3</occupation>
            <occupation name="industry">18.1</occupation>
            <occupation name="services">37.6</occupation>
        </occupations>

        <eximports>
            <eximport name="partners" for="Exports">India 56,5%, Pakistan 29,6%</eximport>
            <eximport name="partners" for="Imports">China 21%, Iran 20,5%, Pakistan 11,8%, Kazakhstan 11%, Uzbekistan 6,8%, Malaysia 5,3%</eximport>
            <eximport name="commodities" for="Exports">opium, fruits and nuts, handwoven carpets, wool, cotton, hides and pelts, precious and semi-precious gems, and medical herbs</eximport>
            <eximport name="commodities" for="Imports">machinery and other capital goods, food, textiles, petroleum products</eximport>
        </eximports>

        <span name="Labor force" align="right">8,478,000 people</span>
        <span name="Agriculture" align="right">opium, wheat, fruits, nuts, wool, mutton, sheepskins, lambskins, poppies</span>
        <span name="Industry" align="right">small-scale production of bricks, textiles, soap, furniture, shoes, fertilizer, apparel, food products, non-alcoholic beverages, mineral water, cement; handwoven carpets; natural gas, coal, copper</span>
    </economy>
    <energy>
        <electrification total="99" urban="98" rural="79" without="18999254" />
        <electricity production="1.211" production_rank="146" consumption="5.526" consumption_rank="119"
                     exports="0" imports="4.4" generating="0.6341" />
        <electricity_source fossil="45" nuclear="0" hydroelectric="52" other_renewable="4" />

        <resource_list>
            <resource name="Crude oil" unit="bbl/day" runit="bbl" production="0" exports="0" imports="0" reserves="0" />
            <resource name="Refined petroleum" unit="bbl/day" production="0" consumption="35000" exports="0" imports="34210" />
            <resource name="Natural gas" unit="million cu m" runit="billion cu m" production="164.2" consumption="164.2" exports="0" imports="0" reserves="49550" />
        </resource_list>
    </energy>
    <communications>
        <phones>
            <phone type="fixed" total="125232" per_100="0" ranking="133" />
            <phone type="cellular" total="21239280" per_100="59.36" ranking="57" />
        </phones>

        <phone_systems>
            <phone_system type="general">progress has been made on Afghanistan's first limited fixed-line telephone service and nationwide optical fiber backbone; aided by the presence of multiple providers, mobile-cellular telephone service continues to improve swiftly; the Afghan Ministry of Communications and Information claims that more than 90% of the population live in areas with access to mobile cellular service; moderate growth through 2024, assuming stable governance and improving economic environment</phone_system>
            <phone_system type="domestic">less than 1 per 100 for fixed-line teledensity; 59 per 100 for mobile-cellular; an increasing number of Afghans utilize mobile-cellular phone networks</phone_system>
            <phone_system type="international">country code - 93; multiple VSAT's provide international and domestic voice and data connectivity</phone_system>
        </phone_systems>

        <internet code="af" users="4717013" percent="13.5" ranking="86" />
        <span name="Broadcast media" align="right">state-owned broadcaster, Radio Television Afghanistan (RTA), operates a series of radio and television stations in Kabul and the provinces; an estimated 174 private radio stations, 83 TV stations, and about a dozen international broadcasters are available</span>
    </communications>
    <transportation>
        <span name="Pipelines" align="top" newline="1">466 km refined products</span>

        <air>
            <air_unit name="Registered carriers">3</air_unit>
            <air_unit name="Aircraft registered by carriers">13</air_unit>
            <air_unit name="Annual passengers transferred">1722612</air_unit>
            <air_unit name="Position in the world">94</air_unit>
            <air_unit name="Heliports">1</air_unit>

            <span name="Annual traffic">29.56 millions mt-km</span>
            <span name="Registration prefix">YA</span>

            <airports total="46">
                <airport min="0" max="913">8</airport>
                <airport min="914" max="1523">6</airport>
                <airport min="1524" max="2437">19</airport>
                <airport min="2438" max="3047">15</airport>
                <airport min="3048" max="9999">5</airport>
            </airports>
        </air>

        <rails total="0" />

        <roads total="34903" ranking="93">
            <road type="paved">17903</road>
            <road type="unpaved">17000</road>
        </roads>

        <water>
            <length>1200</length>
            <ranking>58</ranking>
            <ports>Kheyrabad, Shir Khan</ports>
        </water>
    </transportation>
    <military_and_security>
        <span name="Forces" newline="1">Afghan National Defense and Security Forces (ANDSF) comprised of military, police, and other security elements: Afghan National Army ((ANA), Afghan Air Force, Afghan Special Security Forces, Afghanistan National Army Territorial Forces (ANA-TF)), Afghan National Police (Ministry of Interior), Afghan Local Police (Ministry of Interior), and the National Directorate of Security</span>
        <span name="Expenditures" newline="1">1.2 % of GDP (100th in the world)</span>
        <span name="Personnel strength" newline="1">the Afghan National Defense and Security Forces (ANDSF) have approximately 180,000 active personnel (173,000 Army; 7,000 Air); est. 150,000 Afghan National Police</span>
        <span name="Equipment acquisitions">
            the Afghan Army and Air Force inventory is mostly a mix of Soviet-era and more modern US equipment; since 2010, the US is the leading supplier of arms to Afghanistan, followed by Russia (2019 est.)
            Military service age and obligation: This entry gives the required ages for voluntary or conscript military service and the length of service obligation. Military service age and obligation field listing
            18 is the legal minimum age for voluntary military service; no conscription
        </span>
    </military_and_security>
    <terrorism>
        Haqqani Taliban Network; Harakat ul-Mujahidin; Harakat ul-Jihad-i-Islami; Islamic Jihad Union; Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan; Islamic State of Iraq and ash-Sham-Khorasan Province; Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps/Qods Force; Jaish-e-Mohammed; Jaysh al Adl (Jundallah); Lashkar i Jhangvi; Lashkar-e Tayyiba; al-Qa’ida; al-Qa'ida in the Indian Subcontinent; Tehrik-e-Taliban Pakistan
    </terrorism>
    <transnational_issues>
        <span name="Disputes" newline="1">Afghan, Coalition, and Pakistan military meet periodically to clarify the alignment of the boundary on the ground and on maps and since 2014 have met to discuss collaboration on the Taliban insurgency and counterterrorism efforts; Afghan and Iranian commissioners have discussed boundary monument densification and resurvey; Iran protests Afghanistan's restricting flow of dammed Helmand River tributaries during drought; Pakistan has sent troops across and built fences along some remote tribal areas of its treaty-defined Durand Line border with Afghanistan which serve as bases for foreign terrorists and other illegal activities; Russia remains concerned about the smuggling of poppy derivatives from Afghanistan through Central Asian countries</span>
        <span name="IDPs">2,993,000</span>
        <span name="Illicit drugs" newline="1">
            world's largest producer of opium; poppy cultivation increased 63 percent, to 328,304 hectares in 2017; while eradication increased slightly, it still remains well below levels achieved in 2015; the 2017 crop yielded an estimated 9,000 mt of raw opium, a 88% increase over 2016; the Taliban and other antigovernment groups participate in and profit from the opiate trade, which is a key source of revenue for the Taliban inside Afghanistan; widespread corruption and instability impede counterdrug efforts; most of the heroin consumed in Europe and Eurasia is derived from Afghan opium; Afghanistan is also struggling to respond to a burgeoning domestic opiate addiction problem; a 2015 national drug use survey found that roughly 11% of the population tested positive for one or more illicit drugs; vulnerable to drug money laundering through informal financial networks; illicit cultivation of cannabis and regional source of hashish
        </span>
        <refugees>
            <refugee from="Pakistan" count="72194" />
        </refugees>
    </transnational_issues>
</country>